<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Youssouf Merouani</title>
<link>youssoufmerouani.com/research/</link>
<atom:link href="youssoufmerouani.com/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>The personal website of Youssouf Merouani</description>
<generator>quarto-1.8.25</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2024 23:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Women Inventors: On the Origins of the Gender Patenting Gap</title>
  <link>youssoufmerouani.com/research/2024-01-17_Women-Inventors-On-the-Origins-of-the-Gender-Patenting-Gap/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><strong>ABSTRACT:</strong> The gender patenting gap is well-established and is wide. Despite important progress made over the past decades, the gap remains. Why are women underrepresented in patenting activities? What are the roots of the gender patenting gap? How did the gap evolve since the ‘modern’ patenting system was established? Our knowledge of women’s contribution to innovative activities in the past is extremely scarce. We build an original dataset covering the entirety of French patents to investigate the extent to which women patented relative to men in France during the long nineteenth century and explores the factors behind the historical gender patenting gap. We find that despite the absence of scientific and technical education opportunities for women and the presence of institutional barriers, women, including those who were married, took an active part in the innovation process. The empirical analysis conducted in the paper suggests that explanations of the origins and persistence of the gender patenting gap have to be found outside of the patent system itself.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords</strong>: Patent • Innovation • Gender • Women • Nineteenth Century • France</p>
<p><strong>JEL Codes</strong>: J16, N33, O11</p>
<p><a href="https://portal.research.lu.se/files/169782267/LUPEH_255.pdf">PDF</a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Working Paper</category>
  <guid>youssoufmerouani.com/research/2024-01-17_Women-Inventors-On-the-Origins-of-the-Gender-Patenting-Gap/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2024 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="youssoufmerouani.com/research/2024-01-17_Women-Inventors-On-the-Origins-of-the-Gender-Patenting-Gap/header.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Innovation networks: Dynamics of invention during the French industrialization</title>
  <link>youssoufmerouani.com/research/2023-11-20_Innovation-networks-Dynamics-of-invention/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><strong>ABSTRACT:</strong> This study analyzes two innovation networks in 19th-century France: an inventor-only network and a full network that includes all inventors and patent agents of the period. The inventor-only network displays a sparse, disconnected structure, in contrast to the full network, which shows greater connectivity and cohesion. The analysis reveals different patterns in network connectivity and centrality. The full network follows a power-law distribution, indicating a few influential and central patent agents, unlike the more democratic inventor-only network. The inventors who exhibit relatively central positions are associated with significant cross-industry innovations, while the centrality of patent agents is due to their extensive client networks and industry ties. The study also examines gender and sectoral variations within these networks. Initially, male inventors had higher connectivity, but this trend shifted over time, possibly reflecting changing societal norms and increased women’s empowerment. Sector-wise, female inventors were more actively collaborating in non-traditional fields.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords</strong>: Patent • Innovation • Networks • Patent agents • Nineteenth Century • France</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Work in Progress</category>
  <guid>youssoufmerouani.com/research/2023-11-20_Innovation-networks-Dynamics-of-invention/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2023 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="youssoufmerouani.com/research/2023-11-20_Innovation-networks-Dynamics-of-invention/header.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="124" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Myths and biases: An exploration of Women’s historical patenting activities</title>
  <link>youssoufmerouani.com/research/2023-09-14_Myths-and-biases-An-exploration-of-Womens-historical-patenting-activities/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><strong>ABSTRACT:</strong> This paper explores the representation of women inventors in historical records and uncovers potential biases that influence our current understanding of history. By examining a comprehensive database of nineteenth-century French patents as a case study, we discover that women filed more patents than contemporary biographical records suggest. Further, we illustrate that women’s inventive endeavors spanned all industries, challenging the perception that their contributions were confined to specific sectors. Beyond enhancing our awareness of women’s patenting endeavors, our findings underscore the need to confront systematic biases and exclusionary practices in historical documentation. Such efforts are necessary for fostering a more inclusive and accurate comprehension of women’s contributions to technological development and economic processes.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords</strong>: Patent • Innovation • Gender • Women • Nineteenth Century • France</p>
<p><strong>JEL Classification</strong>: J16, N33, O30</p>
<p><a href="https://econpapers.repec.org/scripts/redir.pf?u=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.cliometrie.org%2Fimages%2Fwp%2FAFC_WP_09_2023.pdf;h=repec:afc:wpaper:09-23">PDF</a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Working Paper</category>
  <guid>youssoufmerouani.com/research/2023-09-14_Myths-and-biases-An-exploration-of-Womens-historical-patenting-activities/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Sep 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="youssoufmerouani.com/research/2023-09-14_Myths-and-biases-An-exploration-of-Womens-historical-patenting-activities/header.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Surviving on the island: linking firm survival and contextual factors in a peripheral region</title>
  <link>youssoufmerouani.com/research/2023-08-04_Surviving-on-the-island-linking-firm-survival-and-contextual-factors-in-a-peripheral region/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><strong>ABSTRACT:</strong> The lion’s share of entrepreneurship research highlights conditions in core regions, while entrepreneurship in peripheral areas has been less studied. This longitudinal study aims at exploring the interplay between the peripheral contexts of island and archipelago communities and firm outcomes - paying special attention to spatial variations and non-linear temporal dimensions. We focus on the survival of all firms active on 17 islands in the Stockholm archipelago, Sweden during a 20-year period (2000-2019). Using longitudinal multilevel modelling, we find that - despite being a seemingly ‘homogeneous’ place - spatial and temporal variations, however small, would have substantial effects on the conditions for everyday entrepreneurship in these communities. Our results show that firms located on islands with higher population density and seasonal dependability face increased probabilities of exit, while access to digital ecosystems, local services in the form of kindergartens, and year-round grocery stores decrease the probabilities of exit. Islands with thicker institutional context, indicating trust and community support, lead to higher survival rates.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords</strong>: Entrepreneurial context • Islandness • Firm survival • Everyday entrepreneurship • Peripherality</p>
<p><a href="https://doi.org/10.4337/9781035320684.00009">Online chapter</a> | <a href="https://www.elgaronline.com/downloadpdf/edcollchap-oa/book/9781035320684/book-part-9781035320684-9.pdf">PDF</a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Published</category>
  <guid>youssoufmerouani.com/research/2023-08-04_Surviving-on-the-island-linking-firm-survival-and-contextual-factors-in-a-peripheral region/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 03 Aug 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="youssoufmerouani.com/research/2023-08-04_Surviving-on-the-island-linking-firm-survival-and-contextual-factors-in-a-peripheral region/color.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Small Island Societies, Livelihoods, Challenges and Opportunities during the Covid-19 Pandemic in Sweden</title>
  <link>youssoufmerouani.com/research/2022-10-31_Small-Island-Societies-Livelihoods-Challenges-and-Opportunities-during-the-Covid-19-Pandemic-in-Sweden/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><strong>ABSTRACT:</strong> Covid-19 increased the social and economic vulnerability of island societies. Swedish islands, key tourism destinations, are also home to many island residents. Previous studies have highlighted the impact of Covid-19 on core areas, but our knowledge of its impact on island communities is lacking. Phenomenology is used to analyse how communities in small Swedish islands perceive the impact of Covid-19. Institutional theory and the concepts of social capital and accessibility are employed in the analysis. Data were collected through semi-structured interviews and focus groups with islanders and representatives of local organizations on sampled islands. Pandemic regulations affected island communities differently. Authorities and shipping companies endeavored to discourage people from visiting islands, which negatively affected tourism in some islands, while tourism increased in others. Informal institutions established a basis for good community relations; they enabled the mobilization of social capital, especially given action by local agents who were endorsed by the community. Cooperation was a key factor in reducing negative impacts. Accessibility increased on islands with well-developed and expanded IT-infrastructure, enabling holiday homeowners to work from their holiday islands. This development helped create a sustained positive economic trend for grocery stores and the construction industry.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords</strong>: Island societies • Covid-19 • institutions • social capital • accessibility</p>
<p><a href="https://doi.org/10.4422/ager.2022.15">PDF</a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Published</category>
  <guid>youssoufmerouani.com/research/2022-10-31_Small-Island-Societies-Livelihoods-Challenges-and-Opportunities-during-the-Covid-19-Pandemic-in-Sweden/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 30 Oct 2022 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="youssoufmerouani.com/research/2022-10-31_Small-Island-Societies-Livelihoods-Challenges-and-Opportunities-during-the-Covid-19-Pandemic-in-Sweden/header.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Ö- och skärgårdsturism under pandemin: Halvtidsrapport och Slutrapport</title>
  <link>youssoufmerouani.com/research/2021-2022_O-och-skargardsturism-under-pandemin-rapporter/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><strong>ABSTRACT:</strong> Ö-samhällen kan rimligtvis antas vara extra sårbara för extern påverkan, inte minst av en sådan chock som utgjorts av Covid-19-pandemin. Dessa rapport bygger på undersökningar som genomförts inom projektet Ö- och skärgårdsturism under pandemin, och innefattar bland annat fokusgrupper och intervjuer med företagare och representanter från en mängd svenska ö- och skärgårdsföreningar.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords</strong>: Ö-samhällen • Svenska öar • Covid-19 • pandemin • skärgårdsturism</p>
<p><a href="https://www.diva-portal.org/smash/get/diva2:1577839/FULLTEXT02.pdf">Halvtidsrapport: PDF</a> | <a href="https://www.diva-portal.org/smash/get/diva2:1653293/FULLTEXT02.pdf">Slutrapport: PDF</a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Report</category>
  <guid>youssoufmerouani.com/research/2021-2022_O-och-skargardsturism-under-pandemin-rapporter/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="youssoufmerouani.com/research/2021-2022_O-och-skargardsturism-under-pandemin-rapporter/header.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Gender and the long-run development process. A survey of the literature</title>
  <link>youssoufmerouani.com/research/2022-09-28_Gender-and-the-long-run-development-process-A-survey-of-the-literature/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><strong>ABSTRACT:</strong> Why do certain countries display high gender equalities while others display low gender equalities? To what extent does gender equality foster economic growth and development? The past decade has witnessed a boom and increasing literature about the role played by women and gender in long-run economic development. The increasing awareness of economics and economic history have contributed to improve our understanding of the crucial role played by women in the process of economic development. This paper reviews the literature on the topic and opens the discussion on current challenges and avenues for future research.</p>
<p><strong>Keywords</strong>: Gender • Women • Development Process • Economic History • Survey</p>
<p><strong>JEL Codes</strong>: J16, N33, O11</p>
<p><a href="https://academic.oup.com/ereh/article/26/4/612/6725763">Online paper</a> | <a href="https://academic.oup.com/ereh/article-pdf/26/4/612/46781444/heac008.pdf">PDF</a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Published</category>
  <guid>youssoufmerouani.com/research/2022-09-28_Gender-and-the-long-run-development-process-A-survey-of-the-literature/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="youssoufmerouani.com/research/2022-09-28_Gender-and-the-long-run-development-process-A-survey-of-the-literature/header.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
